

contact

esfordphd@gmail.com inkedin.com/in/jesford 206.446.6874

website

esford.github.io

GitHub

@jesford

tech skills

♥ Python

pandas, numpy, scipy, pytorch, keras, xgboost, scikit-learn, jupyter, seaborn, matplotlib, prefect, dash, plotly

Git & GitHub
Bash
SQL
C/C++
Travis-CI
AWS & GCP
Sphinx
HTML/CSS
LATEX
OS X
Linux

volunteering

Women in Data Science SLC Ambassador, 2019-now

Salt Lake PyLadies Meetup Organizer, 2017-now

Women in Sci. & Tech. Member, 2018–2020

publications

9 peer-reviewed papers (5 1st-author) & >30 conference presentations (8 invited).

education

Ph.D. in Physics, 2015 University of British Columbia

B.Sc. in Physics, 2008

Minor in Mathematics
University of Nevada, Reno

profile

Experienced Data Scientist with a passion for applied machine learning and open source software. I bring a practical product driven mindset, an obsession with best practices, and a demonstrated ability to collaborate effectively across teams to achieve goals. I am a regular conference speaker at events including PyCon, PluralsightLIVE, and VisInPractice.

experience

2018-current Recursion

Salt Lake City, UT

Senior Data Scientist 11/2019-current

Data Scientist 4/2018-11/2019

- Trained, optimized, and benchmarked deep neural networks (CNNs and graph NNs) to solve problems in drug discovery.
- Technical lead on teams that productionized the first machine learning models at Recursion, responsible for directing a small team of data scientists, and providing regular updates to VPs.
- Model interpretability including saliency maps, GradCAM, DeepDream.
- Pioneered use of MCMC for Bayesian parameter fitting of experimental data, and developed new visualizations to inform biologists.
- Owned creation of cleaned & standardized labelsets from noisy data, enabling comparison of ML models across data science teams.
- Designed & built custom Google Cloud database for storing ML models, metrics, labels, and predictions; created resources for data science users.
- Led data science team to adopt software best practices for reproducible research and clean production quality code.

2016–2018 Backcountry.com

Park City, UT

Data Scientist

- Led design, execution of tests to optimize sales via customer segmentation, product taxonomy, contact method/timing.
- Cross-channel attribution; customer lead scoring; incremental sales.
- Built & deployed interactive dashboards using Plotly Dash.
- Automated processes and pulled disparate data to database summary tables to reduce reporting time for analysts by 99%.
- Built Python package for easily interfacing with Oracle DB from Python, removing multi-tool headache for analytics teams.
- Wrangled messy data from Oracle, Adobe Analytics, Google Trends, Social Media, 3rd-party APIs; enforced data quality across departments.
- Founded and led tutorial and workshop series to elevate technical skills.

2015–2016 **eScience Institute, University of Washington**

Seattle, WA

Data Science Postdoctoral Fellow

- Author of Python package for statistical modeling of galaxy clusters.
- Machine Learning algorithms for hazardous asteroid detection.
- Mentor for the Data Science for the Social Good summer program.

2009–2015 University of British Columbia

Vancouver, BC

Research Assistant / PhD Student

• Complex modeling, uncertainty estimation, sampling, parallel processing.

2007 NASA Jet Propulsion Laboratory

Pasadena, CA

Summer Undergraduate Research Fellowship